<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The. V. abhominable blasphemies co[n]teined in the Masse with a short a[n]swere to them, that saie, we ronne before the kyng and his counsayle.</title>
            <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14361</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108095</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843784</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8540</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14361)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8540)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 635:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The. V. abhominable blasphemies co[n]teined in the Masse with a short a[n]swere to them, that saie, we ronne before the kyng and his counsayle.</title>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Humfrey Powell, dwellyng aboue Holburne conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Do. 1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At end of text: Compiled by John Ueron, Senonois.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The. U. blasphemies conteined in the Masse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8540:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8540:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>THE .V. A B<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOMINABLE BLASPHEMIES <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in the Maſſe, with a ſhort a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere to them, that ſaie, we ronne before the kyng and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayſe.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8540:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8540:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I was mynded (good chriſten rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) to haue made an ende of writynge againſte that curſed and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſacrifice of the Maſſe, but beyng compelled by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate blaſphemye of certayne papiſtes, which euery where do depredicate, and ſaye, that we renne before the kyng and his counſeill (for good chriſten rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, this is their onely refuge, that thei flee to, not hauyng one ſillable in the ſcriptures to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme theyr purpoſe) I am fain to meddell farther in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, and to ſhewe how they go about in ſo ſaiyng, to make the kyng and his counſeill parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of theyr vngodly blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye againſt god, and his ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Whiche thyng maye be
<pb facs="tcp:8540:3"/>prouyd after this maner: Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis poteſtas a domino deo eſt, that is to ſaye: All power is of the lorde god. By the which ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng it foloweth, that generally all kynges, rulers, magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and gouernours, if they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to lyue accordyng to their vocacion, muſt of neceſſitee doe the thyng, that god commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and willeth them to dooe, (for who ſo euer doeth other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whether he be kyng or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, he is no more worthy to be called a prince or gouernour, then the foule ſpiryt, whiche is within a man is to be called his ſoule, ſythe that a prince is vnto the common welthe, that ſame ſelfe thyng, that the ſoule is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body) but this is the chief duetie and office of a kyng or go uernour, to ſeke, promote, and
<pb facs="tcp:8540:3"/>ſet forthe the glory of god, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate and cleane baniſſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye, all ſuch ſtrange worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynges, dreames, and vaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencions of men, as doe in any wiſe obſcure the ſame, deface the mexites of the paſſion of Chriſt, and obliteratte or blotte awaye his death. Now marke ye this argumente, marke ye I ſaye, what foloweth of your ſaiynges yf the kyng and his honorable couceill haue not yet (as ye moſt craftely perſwade vnto the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignorant people, which if it wer not for you would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ioyfully receiue, the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of the ſoonne of god) diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled &amp; put downe the Maſſe. that is to ſaye, the moſte abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, pernicious, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable idolle, that euer Sathan with all his craft coulde inuent
<pb facs="tcp:8540:4"/>then are thei, by your owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, all vngodly, and alſo partakers of your idolatrous blaſphemie, which thing ye ſhal neuer be able to auoide. Sicꝙ vos perduellionis alligatis, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye: ye attache your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of playne and deadly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, againſte the kyng and his honorable counſeill. Whiche all (thankes be vnto the lorde, that hath the hertes of all rulers in his honde) be as farre, in this point, from al vngodlyneſſe and blaſphemye, as ye are now from al truth and veritie, that ſo ſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kepe vp the baner and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darde of your maiſter Sathan. This I ſaye, is the very baner and ſtandard of Sathan the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, whiche he hath ſette vp, to ebſcure, peruert and vtterly ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oliſſhe from the memorye and
<pb facs="tcp:8540:4"/>remembraunce of all men, the death of our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt blindynge all the worlde with moſte peſtilent errour, that is to ſaye with full perſwaſion, that the Maſſe was a ſacrifice, and oblacion to obteyne remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, or a werke wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the prieſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>offereth Chriſte, and they that are participaunt of the ſame, doe deſerue exopere operato, that is to ſaye: of the woorke that is wrought, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyueneſſe of theyr ſynnes, and heauenly ioye, not onely for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be in purgatorye, but alſo for them that be in hell, briefly for all them that are alyue and deade, though it be a. M. yeres ago. Is not this to blaſpheame and diſhonour Chriſte, to burne and oppreſſe his croſſe, to bring his death to perpetuall obliui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:8540:5"/>and forgetfulneſſe, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the fruites of his paſſion, and to euernate and aboliſſhe the ſacrament of his death?</p>
            <p>Theſe fyue abhomynable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemyes I will here with the leaue of god, ſo lyuely depicte, and ſet before the eies of all chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten readers, that the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fauntes and babes ſhall clerely ſee, that they, whiche ſo lewdely affirme that we doe renne afore the kyng and his counſeill, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende nothyng elles, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame their prince, and all them that be about him, with papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hereſye, therwith ſekyng to kepe the true ſubiectes of this illuſtrie realme, in perpetuall blyndneſſe and ignorancye.</p>
            <div n="1" type="blasphemy">
               <pb facs="tcp:8540:5"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is therefore the fyrſt blaſphemy done vnto Chriſte by the maſſe. Chriſt, by the heauenly father, is conſecrated and made high prieſte or high biſſhoppe, not for a tyme (as we doe reade that they were made in the olde teſtament, whoſe prieſtehode, becauſe that they them ſelues were mortall, could not be immortall, and therfore they hadde nede of ſucceſſours, whiche alwaies ſhoulde be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted and made in the rowme of them, that died) but as he is immortall, ſo his prieſthode is euerlaſtyng, and nedeth no ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour. Therfore he was made by the father of heauen, a prieſt for euer after the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chifedech, to execute and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter that prieſthode that endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:8540:6"/>for euer. This miſtery was longe before prefigurated in Melchiſedech, whom after that the ſcripture had ones named to be the prieſt of the liuing god, no more mencion at all, in the ſcriptures is made of hym, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had neuer ended his lyfe. For this ſimilitude is our Meſſias called a prieſte after the order of Melchiſedech. But now, they that vſe this inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſacritice of the Maſſe, muſt nedes daiely to make prieſtes, whom they doe ſubſtitute and ſubrogate vnto Chriſt, as plain ſucceſſours. With the whiche ſubrogacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſubſtituting they do not onely ſpoile Chriſt of his honour, and take from hym the prerogatiue of his euerlaſtyng prieſthode, but alſo go about to plucke hym, frome the ryght
<pb facs="tcp:8540:6"/>honde of god the father, where he can not ſet immortall, except he remayneth a prieſt for euer. Nor thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not thus excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, ſaiyng: that theyr maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng prieſtes are not ſubroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or ſubſtituted vnto Chriſte, as vnto hym, that is ſtill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden with death, but ioygned onely to hym, as ſuffragans of his euerlaſting prieſthode, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che for al them, remaineth with out ende. For the holy apoſtle ſainet Paule concludyng them more narowly, ſaieth plainely that there was in the olde lawe many prieſtes made therefore, becauſe that they were letted by death to continue, ergo ſyth that Chriſt can not be letted by death, be is that one onely prieſt and hath no nede either of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragans, or ſucceſſours. Reade
<pb facs="tcp:8540:7"/>the .v. vii. ix. and .x. to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="blasphemy">
               <head>The .ii. bſaſpbemie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecande abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion of the Maſſe is, that it doeth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terli deface, obſcure, conculcate &amp; treade vnder feete the croſſe and paſſion of Chriſt. Whiche thyng is very euident, for if Chriſt did offer him ſelfe on the croſſe a ſacrifice, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſanctifie vs for euer, &amp; to pourchaſſe euerlaſtynge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcion vnto vs: vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyngly the ſtreingth vertue and efficacie of this ſacrifice, is with out any ende: Elles we ſhoulde iudge no better of Chriſte than of bulles and calues, which wer offered in the olde law. Whiche oblacions were therfore corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted weake and of no effect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:8540:7"/>that thei were oftentymes repeted, iterated and offered of newe againe. Therfore we muſt confeſſe, that ryther this ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſte, whiche he did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the croſſe, doeth lacke and wante the vertue of euerlaſting purificacion clenſyng and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcion, or that it was ones ſufficiently offered for euer.</p>
               <p>Whiche thyng the apoſtle in the ix. and .x. to the Hebrues doeth teſtifie ſaiyng: This high biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Ieſus Chriſte, did appere ones in the ende of the worlde, to put ſyn to flyght, by the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng vp of hym ſelfe. Againe we are by the wyl of god ſanctified, by the offeryng vp of the bodye of Ieſu Chriſte, ones. Item Chriſte did with one oblacion make them perfect for euer, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che are ſanctified: vnto whiche
<pb facs="tcp:8540:8"/>ſaiynges he doeth adde this god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſentence: and where remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe thynges that is to ſaie, of ſinnes, is, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no mo offeryng for ſynne. This thing did Chriſt, whan he did yelde vp the gooſt, ſignifie ſaiyng: Conſummatum eſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaie: It is finiſſhed. With the whiche worde Chriſte doeth teſtifie, that with this one onely ſacrifyce, he hath conſummated perfourmed, and fulfilled, what ſo euer is neceſſary to our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion. But yet not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng we doe daily, vnto this omni ſufficient and moſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte ſacrifice, as though it wer moſte vnperfecte, patche innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable ſacrifices. Sith ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that the holy and ſacred worde of god, doth affyrme pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſte and teſtifye that the vertue
<pb facs="tcp:8540:8"/>of this ſacrifice ones offered for euer, doeth euerlaſtyngly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue: doe not thei, that require any other moſte blaſphemouſly inſimulate and accuſe it of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfeccion &amp; weakeneſſe? Now the maſſe, whiche for that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was inſtituted, that euery daye. MMM. ſacrifices might be offered, what other thyng, I praye, doeth it go about, but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to drowne and burye the paſſion of Chriſte, wherin he did offer him ſelfe a ſufficient ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice vnto his heauenly father? Here euery man, except he be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly blynde, maie ſee, that this is the extreme boldneſſe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than the diuell, whiche repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſo manifeſte and open truthe. But lette vs ſee, with what ſubtiltee this father of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, doeth go about, to cloke his
<pb facs="tcp:8540:9"/>impietye and vngodly inuenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We doe not, ſaieth he, offer ſondry and diuers ſacrifices, but that one ſacrifice onely, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che myſte, with the beames of the light ſonne truthe and veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, is ſone diſcuſſed and driuen away. For Paule doeth not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly affirme, that there remayne no more ſacrifices, but alſo that this one ſacrifice ones offered for euer, can be offered no more. Some men woulde eſcape more ſubtilli and craftily ſaiyng: that thei do not offer it of new again but that thei doe apply the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes therof vnto vs. This vaine ſophiſtrie alſo can eaſily be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, for Chriſt did not offer hymſelfe vpon this condicion, that his ſacrifice ſhulde be eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry daie confirmed and ratified, with newe oblacions, but that
<pb facs="tcp:8540:9"/>with the preachyng of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and miniſtryng of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſouper, the profittes therof ſhulde be communicated to vs. For Paule ſaieth, that Chriſte our paſſeouer is immolated or offered, and therfore he biddeth vs to eate and drinke. &amp;c. This I ſaie, is the right waie to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye this ſacrifice of the croſſe vnto vs, whan we fede vpon the bodye and bloud of Chriſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, either in the holy miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, or in the hearyng and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuyng of his worde faithfully. here I thinke neceſſari, to touch a littell, what they dooe alledge for the chief foundacion of theyr maſſe. God in the fyrſt chap. of Malachie, ſpeaketh after this maner: From the eaſte to the weaſt my name is great emong the gentilles, and in all places
<pb facs="tcp:8540:10"/>encence is offered vp vnto my name, and a pure offeryng alſo, for my name is dreadful emong the gentilles. Here ye maie ſee, ſaie they, that the prophete, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeres before the incarnacion of Chriſte, did prophecie of this holy ſacrifice of the Maſſe. For what other ſacrifice or offeryng ſhoulde he meane? Thou ſhault therfore vnderſtond, good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten reader, that therbe .ii. kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ſacrifices. The one called Propitiatorium or expiatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, that is to ſaie, a ſacrifice, wherwith the wrath of god is pacified, full ſatisfaccion and amendes is made for all theſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the worlde, &amp; the ſinners y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> flye vnto it by faithe, ſo reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei be accoumpted iuſte &amp; rightuous before god. This ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb facs="tcp:8540:10"/>did Chriſt ones offer for euer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> altare of the croſſe, as we haue ſhewed by the worde of god. And for this cauſe, were al y ſacrifices of the olde lawe whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che did prefygurate that one onely ſacrifice, called propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories. The other is called Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſticum, that is to ſaie a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of thankes geuyng, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che comprehendeth all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of charitee and loue. For by it we honour god in his lymmes we doe offer vnto him our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, laudes and thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, whiche by the ſtrength of that other ſacrifice are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto god. That therfore Malachie did meane this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyce, we wyll proue by ſtrong ſcriptures, whiche the papiſtes ſhall neuer bee able to auoyde.
<pb facs="tcp:8540:11"/>Let my praier, O lorde, ſaieth dauid, aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp before thy ſight as encence. C .xli. pſalme. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine Paule co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth vs to offer our bodyes, a liuely ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and reaſonable worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng. Item Paule doeth call the liberalitye of the Philipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wher with thei did refreſſhe hym, an offeryng of ſwete ſmell. Alſo Oſee doeth call our than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes geuyng the calues of our lip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, whiche Dauid doeth call the ſacrifice of laude and praiſe And Paule in the .xiii. to the Hebrues, the fruites of our lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes that confeſſe the name of the lorde. wherby any man may ſee, that Malachie did in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd place vnderſtonde this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſacrifice of thankes geuyng, as holy Hierome in his commen taries vpon the foreſaide place,
<pb facs="tcp:8540:11"/>doeth teſtifie. Reade the place who will. Now haue I proued by the ſcriptures, that Malachi helpeth them nothyng, but that this ſacrifice of the Maſſe, is a new inuencion of Sathan, to deface the croſſe and paſſion of Chriſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="blasphemy">
               <head>The .iii. blaſphemie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow we will come to the thyrde blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye, and proue that the Maſſe doeth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate and driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the memory of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that precious and moſte whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome death of Chriſt. For as the approuyng of the teſtament or laſte wil of a man, dependeth of his death: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtament wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our lorde Ieſus Chriſt did be queſt vnto vs fre remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our
<pb facs="tcp:8540:12"/>ſynnes, and euerlaſting rightu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſeneſſe, was confyrmed and approued by his death. They y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doe immutate, alter, or change any thynge in this teſtament, dooe denye his deathe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt it for naught. But what is the maſſe but a new &amp; cleane contrary teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doeth not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, of theyr maſſes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe a new remiſſion of ſynnes, and a new acquiſicion or pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſſyng of rightuouſenes? We haue now as many teſtamentes as we haue maſſes. Let Chriſte come therfore, &amp; with an other death, yea with infinite deathes confirme the innumerable teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes of the maſſes. That ther fore that I haue ſayed, is very true. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of the maſſe, that one onely and true death of Chriſt, is obliterated and cleane
<pb facs="tcp:8540:12"/>blotted awaie. Would not theſe maſſarie prieſtes, if it laye in theyr power, ſlaye Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of newe? for Paule ſaieth: where the teſtament is, ther the deathe of the teſtatour or teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maker, muſte be betwene. The maſſe is accoumpted to be the teſtament of Chriſt: ergo it requireth his deathe. Beſydes that, the hoſte, which is offered, muſte bee ſlayne. If Chriſte is ſacrificed in euery Maſſe: then he muſt be ſlayne, moſte cruelly euery daie in a. M. places. This is not myne. but ſainet Paules argument, whiche ſaieth, If he hadde nede to offer hym ſelfe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener, then he ſhulde had nede to haue dyed many tymes, ſens the begynnyng of the worlde. Now ye maie ſee what goodneſſe is in this abhominable Maſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="blasphemy">
               <pb facs="tcp:8540:13"/>
               <head>The .iiii. blaſphemie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth detriment or harme that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the maſſe, is that it taketh awaie from vs, the fruites of the death of Chriſte. For who will acknowlage or thinke, that he is redemed, by the deathe of Chriſte, when he ſeeth, a newe redempcion in the maſſe? Who will truſte that his ſynnes are forgeuen, when he ſeeth euery daie a newe remiſſion afore his eyes? And ſurely thei that ſaie, that in the maſſe we doe obteine remiſſion of our ſynnes, onely becauſe that it was before pour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaſſed by the death of Chriſte, can not this eſcape. For this is none other thyng, but to ſaie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are therfore bought and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demed
<pb facs="tcp:8540:13"/>of Chriſte, becauſe that we ſhoulde redeme our ſelues. This is the doctrine ſet forth by Sathan, whiche with fier and ſwerde, they dooe ſo ſtiffely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende, and vpholde. We doe (ſay thei) offer Chriſt in the maſſe, that by this oblacion, we maie obteine remiſſion of ſinnes, and bee partakers of the paſſion of Chriſte. What is then the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, but an exaumple, wherby we ſhulde learne to bee our one redemers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="blasphemy">
               <head>The .v. blaſphemie.</head>
               <p>NOw I come to the fyft ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominacion, howe by the maſſe, the holy ſouper, in the whiche the lorde left vnto vs the remembrance of his paſſion, is vtterly cancelled and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie from vs. For the ſouper of
<pb facs="tcp:8540:14"/>the lorde, is a gifte which, with thankes geuyng ſhuld be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, where as the ſacrifice of the maſſe, is a price or rewarde offe red vnto god to bee receiued of hym, for a ſatisfaction and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes. Loke what difference is betwene geuyng &amp; receiuing, that ſame is betwixt this word ſacrament, and this worde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. And ſurely by this, doeth the wretched vnthankefulneſſe, and ingratitude of man declare it ſelfe. For where man ſhoulde haue acknowlaged the gratuit benignitee of the liuyng god, &amp; geuen thankes vnto him, in that he maketh god his debter. The ſacrament did promyſe, that we were by the death of Chriſt, not for ones reſtored to lyfe, but ſtyl continually viuified, becauſe that then our ſaluacion, was
<pb facs="tcp:8540:14"/>fully accoumpliſſhed. But the Maſſe ſingeth an other ſonge, that is to ſaie, that Chriſt muſt be daiely offered for vs, therby to obteine reſtitucion of lyfe. the ſouper of the lorde, was diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion emong the faithfull, to aduertyſe vs, that we ſhuld be al one in chriſt Ieſu. This communion the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſſe, hath cleane baniſſhed awaie from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregacoin and hath brought in, in ſtede therof, a very excommu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicacion, as I haue ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed before, in the preface of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe. Do not now the very blynde ſee, the deaf, heare, &amp; the very infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes vnderſtond, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is the abhominacion, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng reached for the in a golden cuppe, did inebriate and made dronken, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges and people
<pb facs="tcp:8540:15"/>of the yearthe, from the hygheſt to the loweſt, cam ſingyng as brute beaſtes, and vnreaſonable creatures, to put their whole hope &amp; confidence in this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious puddel of idolatry, &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual fornicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For this is the adulterous Helene, for whoſe ſake, al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemies of the trueth, do ſo rageouſly contend, ſtriue &amp; expugne the kingdom of Chriſt, his true doctrine and goſpell. This I ſaie, is the adulterous Helene, with whom all the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes thorough out al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, doe committe deadly fornicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and adultery. But bleſſed be that puyſſaunt lorde of hoſtes, whiche of his tender loue and mercy, hath preſerued our moſt ſoueraine lorde and prynce Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the ſyxt, from the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng lyppes of this adulterouſe
<pb facs="tcp:8540:15"/>harlotte, whiche hath ſo by the ſpace of theſe .v. hundreth yeres and more deceiued all nacions, alluryng them from their true ſpouſe &amp; houſband Ieſu Chriſt, to all kyndes of abhominacion and filthyneſſe: Oh how muche bounde are we all, whiche haue any zeale to the goſpel of Chriſt to laude and praiſe that almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty and mercifull father, whiche hath prouided ſuch a noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectour and defendour, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all the kynges dominions &amp; realmes, but alſo of all truthe and veritee, whiche at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tyme Sathan dooeth not ceaſſe with his miniſters to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne and aſſaile on euery ſyde: calumniatynge the true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers therof, as though in this matter, thei ſhulde renne before the kyng &amp; his honorable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceil
<pb facs="tcp:8540:16"/>ſurely is nothyng els, but which to accuſe their prince &amp; gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, with all his honorable counſeilours of playne blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt god and his worde, whiche to dooe is no leſſe, than deadly treaſon, as I haue ſaied before, Beware therfore, and ceaſſe to beare your ſelues, in this your abhominacion, by your prince or any of his hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable counſeill, whiche all doe deteſte, abhorre and hate, all ſuche idolatrous blaſphemye, being alwaies ready with all theyr myght and endeuoure to ſeke, ſet forthe, &amp; promote, the glory of almighty god, to whom with the ſoonne and the holy gooſt, bee prayſe glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for euer. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8540:16"/>
            <head>Compiled by Iohn Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, Senonois.</head>
            <p>Imprintyd at London, by Humfrey Powell, dwellyng Aboue Hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burne conduit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>AN. Do. 1548.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
